Guide to the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9: Trusteeship Records WAG.149
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9: Trusteeship Records
1975-1995
WAG.149
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.0 linear feet (3 boxes)
Following the murder of James Bishop, ousted leader of the IBPAT, District Council 9, on May 17, 1990, an investigation by city, state and federal law enforcement agencies revealed the layers of corruption that pervaded the Council. Six weeks later, the top officials of the District Council, along with two mob-connected contractors, were indicted on bribery and racketeering charges. Seven months after the indictments, when the officials were pleading guilty and resigning from office, IBPAT President William Duvall appointed John Alfarone, President of Local 1974 to serve as Trustee of District Council 9. This action precipitated a battle within the international union's General Executive Board. Duval's opponents made an effort to remove Alfarone as Trustee, but the attempt failed. The trusteeship came to an end in the spring of 1992. The collection contains materials related to the internal activities of the IBPAT and various locals in the District Council 9, and materials related to the investigation of racketeering within the Council, including warrants for wiretapping and progress reports issued to the court on the need for continued surveillance. Press clippings, correspondence, affidavits, indictments and hearing transcripts are also included.
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City.
Provenance
The International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9: Trusteeship Records were donated to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by John Alfarone on March 13, 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
James Bishop, ousted leader of IBPAT, District Council 9, was murdered on May 17, 1990 by operatives of the Lucchese Crime Family. The former secretary-treasurer's murder led to the unraveling of the District Council's leadership, as the ensuing investigation by city, state and federal law enforcement agencies revealed the layers of corruption that pervaded the Council. Six weeks later, the top officials of the District Council, along with two mob-connected contractors, were indicted on bribery and racketeering charges. All but one (against whom charges were later dropped) pleaded guilty and were sentenced to jail. The indictments by the Manhattan District Attorney's office were the result of an intensive two-year investigation into corruption in the painting industry. City, state and federal prosecutors collaborated in the probe. Bishop was murdered by the mob because they correctly suspected that he was talking with the government investigators.
The international union was slow to react to the troubles in the New York City District Council, one of the largest in the country. No action was taken until the indictments were released. At that point, General President William Duval assigned international vice president James Damery to conduct an investigation. The effort was seriously compromised by the fact that Damery's conduit for membership complaints was international representative William Courtien, named in the indictment as one of the coordinators of the enterprise conspiracy. Seven months after the indictments, when the officials were pleading guilty and resigning from office, President Duval appointed John Alfarone, President of Local 1974 to serve as Trustee of District Council 9. This action precipitated a battle within the international union's General Executive Board. Duval's opponents made an effort to remove Alfarone as Trustee, but the attempt failed.
Alfarone's long-running legal battle to thwart the efforts of organized crime to destroy the Tapers local earned him a reputation as a fighter of corruption. He had a reputation for independence and was a fierce opponent of the old, mob-linked leaders. As the newly-appointed Trustee of DC 9, he committed himself to a program of reform. At a membership meeting on May 18th, 1991 Alfarone reported that the U.S. Department of Justice would institute court action to impose a federal trusteeship over DC 9 unless the union acted to rid itself of organized crime control.
Upon taking over as Trustee, Alfarone dissolved the District Council, cancelled the elections and the proposed referendum on the District Council by-laws scheduled for June, instituted fiscal reforms, ordered a change in job and shop stewards, and directed organizers to patrol job sites. Alfarone issued periodic reports to General President Duval on the status of the trusteeship. Duval was still embroiled in his own fight to maintain his position, against opponents who outnumbered him on the General Executive Board.
The trusteeship came to an end in the Spring of 1992. In June of that year an election was held in the District Council for the top position of secretary-treasurer and for six business agent positions.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains materials related to the internal activities of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades (IBPAT), internal activities of various locals in the New York City District Council, and materials related to the investigation of racketeering within the Council, including warrants for wiretapping and progress reports issued to the court on the need for continued surveillance. Press clippings, correspondence, affidavits, indictments and hearing transcripts are also included. The reports of the Trustee and some agendas for DC 9 meetings are particularly significant, as are graphic descriptions present in the indictments of the various methods by which the mob exerted its domination of the union.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into one series:
I, General Files, 1975-1995
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Photographs (Photos 131)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Photographs (Photos 150)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Records (Wagner 42)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 874 Records (Wagner 152)
Frank Schonfeld Photographs (Photos 144)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Records (Wagner 150)
Frank Schonfeld Papers (Wagner 27)
Alfarone, John.; Bishop, James.; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 490 (New York, N.Y.).; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 848 (New York, N.Y.).; Duval, William A.; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City.; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Collective labor agreements |x Painters, Industrial |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Hearings (event); Indictments (legal documents).; Labor union democracy |z New York (State); Labor unions |x Corrupt practices |z New York (State); Legal documents.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); Painters, Industrial |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Painters, Industrial |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: General Files, 1975-1995.
  - Alfarone, John (Trustee): Daily Planner, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alvin Blyer (National Labor Relations Board) v. Local 1974, Drywall, Tapers and Painters, International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council No. 9(United States District Court CV-92 3558): Stipulation and Order, Jul 31, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Building and Construction Trades Council: Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burkhardt, Frank: Curriculum Vitae and Job Description, Dec 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Burkhardt, Frank: Police and Medical Reports, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bylaws and Constitutions, 1975-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Consolidated Edison Company of New York: National Maintenance Agreements, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Constitutionalist(Rank and File Publication), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conventions, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jul 26, 1977-Mar 11, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Mar 12, 1991-Nov 19, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Nov 20, 1991-Oct 8, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: District Council 9, Jan 31, 1986-Dec 27, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Legal, Feb 5, 1980-Sep 23, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Locals, Aug 27, 1988-Jul 13, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Officers (District Council 9 and Locals), May 9, 1989-May 28, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Duval, William A. (General President, International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades): Address to Special Convention, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General: Contracts, Correspondence and Reports, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - J ohn Alfarone, Joseph Giordano and Brian Gordon v. Standard Drywall Corp., Arnold Koslow, ELD Realty Co. and ELD Realty Company No. 4(United States District Court CV-81-015): Deposition of Brian Gordon, Jun 6, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jurisdictional Disputes (Service Employees International Union, International Union of Operating Engineers), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Local 1974, Drywall Tapers and Painters, International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades District Council #9 and A.F.C. Enterprises(Arbitration), Jul 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Local Unions: Rosters, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes (including General Executive Board), 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Monroe, Michael E.: Cases Relating to Assault and Battery, 1977, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Monroe, Michael E.: Motion to Charge with Violation of the IBPAT General Constitution (General Correspondence), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Monroe, Michael E.: Motion to Charge with Violation of the IBPAT General Constitution (Letters in Favor), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Monroe, Michael E.: Motion to Charge with Violation of the IBPAT General Constitution (Letters in Opposition), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New York State Supreme Court: Application for an Eavesdropping and Surveillance Warrant, Sep 29, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New York State Supreme Court: Application for a Second Extended and Amended Eavesdropping and Surveillance Warrant, Nov 27, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York State Supreme Court: Application for a Third Extended and Amended Eavesdropping and Surveillance Warrant, Dec 20, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - New York State Supreme Court: Application for a Fourth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping and Surveillance Warrant, Jan 10, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - New York State Supreme Court: Application for a Fifth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping and Surveillance Warrant, Feb 5, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for an Eavesdropping Warrant, May 10, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for an Extended Eavesdropping Warrant, Jun 7, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Second Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Jul 6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Third Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Aug 2, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Fourth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Aug 30, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Fifth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Sep 27, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Sixth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Oct 25, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Seventh Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Nov 20, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for an Eighth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Dec 18, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Ninth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Jan 16, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for a Tenth Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Jan 30, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York State Supreme Court Appellate Division: Application for an Eleventh Extended and Amended Eavesdropping Warrant, Feb 27, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Painters District Council No. 8, et al v. General Vice President Michael E. Monroe(International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades Trial Board): Exhibits, Motions, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Painters DC 8 v. Monroe: Transcript, Dec 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Painters Local Union No. 913 and 15 of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trade v. A.L Monroe, Fred C. Hagen, Michael E. Monroe, James Damery, Patrick L. Lane, Walter G. Raftery(United States District Court, Northern California C 91-3546 TEH): Decisions and Motions, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Painters Local 913 and 15, et al v. Monroe, et al: Memoranda, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Painters Local 913 and 15, et al v. Monroe, et al: Statements, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Painters Local 913 and 15, et al v. Monroe, et al: Transcript, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - People of the State of New York v. Aaron Lefkowitz: Plea, Mar 1, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - People of the State of New York v. Daniel Rech: Plea, Mar 18, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - People v. Rech, et al: People's Response to Defendant's Omnibus Motion, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - People of the State of New York v. Edward Capaldo: Plea, Mar 6, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - People v. Capaldo, et al: Indictment, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - People of the State of New York v. Edward Filancia: Plea, Mar 8, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - People of the State of New York v. Frank Arnold: Plea, Sep 24, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - People of the State of New York v. Joseph Candiano: Plea, Mar 8, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - People of the State of New York v. Paul Kamen: Plea, Mar 6, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - People v. Kamen: People's Response to Defendant's Omnibus Motion, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - People of the State of New York v. Peter Chiodo: Plea, Sep 24, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - People of the State of New York v. Peter Chiodo, Anthony Casso, Frank Arnold: Indictment, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - People of the State of New York v. Salvator Savarese: Plea, Mar 8, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - People of the State of New York v. Seymour Strelzik: Indictment, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pension Fund: Balance Sheets, Financial Statements, Annuity Plan, Benefit Fund Analyses, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Pension Fund: Balance Sheets, Financial Statements, Annuity Plan, Benefit Fund Analyses, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Press Clippings and Releases, 1988-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rank and File: Correspondence and Fliers, 1980-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Tax Forms: District Council 9 (990, LM-2, LM-6, LM1-A), 1990- 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tax Forms: International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades (LM-2, LM-15, LM16), 1984-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Tax Forms: Local 1486 and 1974 (990, LM-2), 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Trial Board Hearing (Bernie Donovan, Robert Myers): Transcript, pp 2-124, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Trial Board Hearing (Bernie Donovan, Robert Myers): Transcript, pp 125-244, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Trustee's Reports, Mar 24, 1991-Jun 26, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Exhibits (Hearing Officer), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Exhibits (Loria and Schonfeld), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Exhibits (Special Trustee) 1-4, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Exhibits (Special Trustee) 5-14, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Exhibits (Special Trustee) 15-20, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 1-118, Mar 26, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 119-244, Mar 26, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 245-353, Mar 27, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 354-457, Mar 27, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 458-551, Mar 28, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Trusteeship Hearings: Transcript, pp 552-648, Mar 28, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The United States of America v. James Woolford and Richard Campigotto: Indictment, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The United States of America v. Michael Monroe: Charge Sheet, Oct 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - West Virginia Paint and Tank Company: Agreement, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - West Virginia Paint and Tank Company: Employees' Registration Forms, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)